such disgusting
monsters, you know, that that we but
retribution is the is at the bottom of
our list is at the bottom of my list.
The top of my list is any single child
[music]
getting the help that it is going to
need to transcend
the horror that none of us will ever
ever be able to even begin to understand
of of what's [music] been done to them
in Palestine since 1948. I'm not just
talking about since O September the 7th,
2023. [music]
I'm talking about 80 years of mon of a
monster, a rampant raging
ethno [music] and religio supremacist
monster.
[music]
Hi, I'm John Kuryaku and welcome back to
Deep Focus. It seems like things just
get worse and worse and worse by the day
in Palestine, specifically in Gaza. But
there are problems in the West Bank as
well. The United Nations declared that
there is an actual famine taking place
in Gaza. A famine. Men, women, children,
the elderly, the sick are starving to
death in a country that has plenty of
food for everybody. The Israeli
government just won't allow that food to
reach the people who need it the most.
This is a war crime. It's a crime
against humanity. It's a form of
genocide. And that's not John saying it.
That's the United Nations saying it.
That's the International Court of
Justice saying it. Well, we're going to
talk about that issue and others in the
region with a personal hero of mine.
Roger Waters is one of the co-founders
of the rock group Pink Floyd. He's one
of the four or five biggestselling
musical acts in the history of the
planet. But Roger has used his fame, his
notoriety, and even his money to support
human rights, civil rights, and civil
liberties. And he's been especially
concerned about the people of Gaza.
Roger, thank you so much for joining us.
It's always such a pleasure to have you.
>> I'm very happy to be here. Good to see
you again.
>> Good to see you. I'd like to start with
the situation on the ground in Gaza if
we could. There's plenty of food, of
course, but the Israeli government
simply won't allow it into the Gaza
Strip. This is a war crime, but all we
see is international hand ringing. Why
is food not getting into Gaza? And can
countries other than Israel and the US
force it to happen?
Countries could if it was a part of
their what they consider to be their
mandate. What's what's becomes
increasingly interesting about this is
the disconnect between what we have
always been led to believe about
governments particularly western liberal
dem democratic so-called countries and
the way they work and the whether or not
they're supposed to express their
opinions and feelings and political
inclinations of the populace or not and
so on and so forth. And so this is a
real awakening for pe people of I'm 81
years old and I always thought that
after the second world war we had
decided a that we didn't want to commit
genocide like the Nazis did between 1933
and 1945. That was one thing and that
and and that also we were going to agree
which we did on December the 10th 1948
and a basic requirement to observe basic
human rights as a matter of
international law all over the world. So
I grew up believing that that was
reality and now I know it's not. Okay.
So, so
looking into this first of all, every
every day that we observe what's
happening to our brothers and sisters in
Palestine and more specifically to the
children in Gaza, the innocents, the
absolute pure innocents in Gaza who are
being murdered on a daily basis by the
state of Israel with the absolute
complicit agreement and applause of the
United States, the United Kingdom,
Germany, France, Holland, blah blah blah
everybody with the possible exceptions
of the Spanish and maybe you know the
South Africans and so on. So but that's
a separate conversation about the ICJ
and what went on and what didn't go on
and what they have and haven't found.
Fascinating by the way that the Ugandan
judge it turns out is a raging Christian
Zionist who believe whose belief in God
trumps absolutely all feelings for other
human beings. she is going to go on
lying and to and and uh not observing
international notwithstanding the fact
that she's the vice president of the ICJ
in the H because God has told her that
end times are coming and she has to play
her part.
F me. I nearly used dropped the fbomb
then because you can't make this [__]
up, can you? and that she was they were
15 to1 or 14 to1 of voting you know with
the ICJ back then in January it's now
August this is 7 months ago it's
incredible and yet the genocide
continues unabated and it's now reaching
its climax where they're murdering
everyone in the West Bank as well as
everyone in Gaza and they're completely
open about it and our governments are
all going yep carry on you're just
depending yourselves. Bull [__] It's
obvious complete nonsense. It's an
absolute abrogation of everything that
we thought we stood for. So, so here we
find ourselves waking up every morning
wiping away the tears
and wondering what to do today. My today
I'm going to talk to John Kiryaku on the
telly and we're going to have a
conversation. Nobody will take any
notice obviously because what are we
driven by? We're driven by we we live in
a world the western world. I can't talk
about the Chinese or the Russians for
anybody. I'm not I don't speak Russian
so I don't feel
you know Gilbert Dro obviously does
speak Russian and so does Ray Mc you
know Ry speaks Russian and various I
don't so I can't really claim to have
much of a insight into what goes in
Russia but from my observation and what
I hear ordinary Russian people saying in
translation it feels to me as they're
very much like me and John Kiryako and
the rest of us and all of those to go,
"Hold on a minute. We're human beings.
This isn't what we want. Why is it?"
It's because it's what they want. It's
what Jeff Bezos wants. It's what Mark
Zucker wants. It's what Bill Gates
wants. It's what the ruling class want.
They want to maximize the bottom line
for their shareholders and for
themselves. And they want to go on
getting richer and richer and richer.
It's not enough for them that they're
worth $200 billion.
They want to be worth a trillion
dollars. They want they would actually
prefer it if there were only 10 of them
in the world and they owned everything
and the rest of us were slaves. And that
is what is going on. So the scales are
falling from our eyes. We always
believed them when they said never
again.
But they didn't mean it. And these thugs
in Israel, this appalling, murderous,
filthy, disgusting, racist, apartate
state, the state of Israel has failed.
It is a failed state and we all know it.
All of us know it. Ordinary people all
over the world know it. The the
governments are not going to do anything
about this at all. possibly within the
political arena. We saw one glimmer of
light yesterday in England and that was
Jeremy Corbyn starting a new party that
was going to supposedly um represent the
feelings of the working class in the UK
who as we know before the invasion of
Iraq in 2003
took to the streets 2 million of them
and they were part of they were part of
a demonstration in March 2003 to stop
the invasion. of Iraq by over 20 million
people worldwide took to the streets
going, "This is insane." And it was
insane. And it was all based on lies,
just like all foreign policy is always
based on lies. Particularly the foreign
policy of uh of the United States Empire
for instance. before that to go back I
made a speech to um
uh there was an anniversary of Yaltta 80
years before it well 80 years since
Yaltta which was in in February I think
and and I there was a conference and
they asked me to speak so I made it and
I said you know it may be that Gaza
what's happening in Gaza is actually
providing us with the pool of narcissus
and when we look into it we see our own
reflection refction
I say and the reflection shows us
particularly we who are British
the British Empire was
post the Romans probably the most evil
empire that there has been in the whole
history of empires and we've slaughtered
more people than the this new bunch of
thugs in the North America will ever
dream of except they do have nuclear
weapons now and they do look as if
they're going to use them and they are
the only country that's ever used
nuclear weapons as we know because we've
just had the anniversary of of Hiroshima
from that you know it's weird but um VJ
night is my earliest memory. I looked
>> oh my
>> I looked out of a window in a little
council house on Cherenton Road in
Cambridge and I told my mother this and
she stared at me I when I wasn't very
old when I told her the memory and she
said that's amazing. I said why is that
amazing? She said, "Because you're
describing VJ night." Cuz I said, "There
were people. There was a bonfire and
people were happy and they were dancing
and there was a brown sofa and a dog and
a funny door that went to an upstairs
room that looked like a piece of cheese
cut off." And I described it very well.
I I was less I wasn't going to be two
for another 3 months cuz I was born in
September 1943 and this was in whenever
it was July. No, August August 13th. I
think it was 1945. Yeah.
>> Anyway, I digress and I will I tend to
digress and I tend to ramble
>> because it's the only thing that um
stops me bursting into tears, frankly.
>> That's right. Because
>> I I want to ask I want to ask your
opinion on something that I've noticed
the Israeli government has actually been
very successful with and that is
convincing so many people especially in
the United States and in Western Europe
that this whole problem began on October
7th. They say that their goal is to
destroy Hamas. Well, Hamas for all
intents and purposes no longer exists,
at least not as a fighting force. And
besides, even before October 7th, how
many planes, how many tanks and
artillery pieces did did Hamas have?
>> None.
>> None. So the the Israeli goal here seems
clear to me. It's it's ethnic cleansing,
which is to push all Palestinians out of
Gaza.
>> Yeah.
>> Now, that is it's clearly obviously
illegal. It's a war crime. It's a crime
against humanity. And yet
the the self-described most civilized
countries in the world are just standing
by watching it happen. And you know that
the same thing is happening in the West
Bank at the same time.
How can how can those of us who are not
in positions of authority, people like
you or me,
>> how can we fight against this?
>> I'm going to tell you now. I'm going to
tell you right now. I'm going to just
open this up here. over there some uh
let me just Yeah, I I recently made um I
I've been making a new song and it's
slowly escaping.
>> All right. And it's called Sumud
and when I we could play it if I if I we
could play it or I will send it to you.
You can play it on a future program if
you want because it's beginning to
escape now. Um
I'm going to just read you the beginning
of it so you understand where it is. At
the beginning of it uh there is a voice
over to the introduction and and it says
there is a word in Arabic sumud
it means steadfast perseverance
particularly in resistance to the
occupation of your homeland. And then it
goes on to and it's a poem about how all
I want and I dream of is when voices
join in harmony. And I begin to describe
what it might be like if we all sang
together as a choir in resistance to the
infamy of whatever. So that's the first
verse. The second verse uh drives drives
them completely insane. They tried to
have all my tours cancelled. I I I did
this is not a drill in 2022 in North
America and Mexico and then all over
Europe and then all over South America
>> and um there's a song that that I did in
it called the powers that be and during
that song I mentioned the names among
many others of Shireen Abuaklay who as
you know but some of your audience may
not uh was a a Palestinian American
um [clears throat] journalist who was
murdered on the outskirts of Janine
two years ago now. Um, so she and the
other name that I mentioned which is
what drove them crazy is Anne Frank who
is you also know was a was a much
younger uh woman. She was like
13year-old about that age um Jewish girl
who was murdered in Holland by the Nazis
uh in 1943.
And they have one thing in common. And
oh oh and the other name that I
mentioned at the very beginning is
Rachel Cy who was an American protester
who was murdered in 2002 I believe very
very early on long before I became
involved in any of this. Run over by an
Israeli bulldozer trying to prevent the
demolition of a some Palestinian
person's home by the Israelis. And so
that so that's that. Okay. So and I
won't read all of the stuff. So that's
that. There's it's a list of martyrs.
The second thing, but but in at the end
of this verse, the second verse of the
thing, it says there's Iman Alhams and
Anne Frank and Sophie Skull and blah
blah. It says, "Help me to open their
eyes from up in the penthouse. We must
all look like ants to them. Wake up,
[__] We are women and men.
Well up, unashamed, my bleeding heart.
Give me an Oh, yeah. Join us in
harmony." So I'm imploring imploring
people to join the choir and make a loud
noise. The last verse
talks about it says then across the
great divide come men and women unafraid
to dash in loss their bracelets at the
wall bleeding hearts like you and me.
All right but there are billions of us
all over the world. Uh and it says
um when voices join in harmony and we
turn the final page when man evolves
beyond the crass and reason comes of age
and then there's a list and dogma and
witchcraft and can't and propaganda and
palanteer and lo heed and groomman and
chevron and excellent fiser and the
oligarchs and misers say we're sorry
that we done it mummy we only done it
for the [__] money. Oh yeah, just for
the money. Oh yeah, just for the cash.
And it goes on uh it says, "When voices
join in harmony, we will make a joyful
sound. We will follow our own moral
compass. We won't let their slight of
hand trump us. We'll find 10,000 new
voices in every crowd. When all those
new voices join us in harmony,
standing shouldertosh shoulder from the
river to the sea,
people from every nation will hear that
joyful sound. Ordinary people just
standing their ground and together these
ordinary people together they will turn
this ship around. Okay. And that's sort
of so that is the that the message of my
song is that this will not be changed by
K star or Donald Trump or any of them.
This will be changed in the end by
billions of ordinary people with hearts
and souls and empathy
standing shouldertosh shoulder in face
of this obvious criminally insane
policy.
at the policy of the Israeli government
which says God told us that he's behind
us and we should kill everybody else on
earth because it belongs to us and and
that it's good and that might that might
should mean right and that whoever's got
the most weapons should just steal
everything and rape and plunder and
there should be no international law.
That's the why United States never
signed up to the Treaty of Rome. They
don't want international law. They don't
believe. You know, when I was 15 years
old, I was a a ordinary grammar school
in England and I once spoken a debate.
It's the only time I've ever stood up
and debated anything. And and I can
remember it now. And it said, "This
house believes in the idea of world
government."
Well, that's what the Hag is about.
That's what the rule of international
law is about. It's about the whole world
and all the human beings on it being
governed by a system of international
law that we are all required to obey.
Well, the Trumps and the Snowmers and
the Netanyahus and the smoke riches,
they don't believe in any of that
[__] They say, "No, we believe in
killing people and stealing their land.
That's what we believe in. And we always
did. And and it's and it didn't start on
October the 7th. We've believed this
since the Mayflower landed in the 1640s
in North America. That was our Zion. And
we killed everybody. There's a very few
left. I know them. They're friends of
mine. I'm very close with the Shinikok
nation where I live in in northeastern
United States of America.
So this is very very recent history.
This only goes back to 300 years. It's a
blink in the history of this old star
that we call the sun. Anyway, you remind
me of a of a story that you told several
years ago. We were both speaking at an
event here in Washington for the
Washington Report and you talked about
approaching entertainers who had been
very active in the anti-aparttheid
movement and were and were instrumental
in many ways in bringing down a
parttheid
>> yet they didn't they didn't want to get
involved uh with Palestine and their
message to you I remember was actually
consistent. It was that the issue was
complicated. Yeah,
>> that was the the word that they kept
using and you said actually it's not
very complicated.
>> It's pretty straightforward where
innocent people are dying for no reason.
>> And so here we are 3 years later. Has
that changed in any way?
>> No, they're still they're still
trottting out exactly the same [__]
They're still saying that all of this is
just a response to the heinous attack by
Hamas on October the 7. No, the attack
by Hamas on October the 7th is a natural
reaction. It's part of Sumud, you know,
which is a perseverance in the
resistance to the occupation of
Palestinian land that has been going on
since the Nakba which started on the
10th of May in 1948. So there's nothing
new about this. October the 7th is an
absolute side issue. It's not not is it
just completely natural and normal that
the indigenous people of an occupied
land will resist and they will use
military force if they are able to or or
if they can. And it's not just that they
will do that. It's that they have every
right to do that. They're required
morally and even by under international
law to res to respond. they have
absolute right to respond militarily to
the occupation. So it's all be none of
this has ever been compliment
complicated. You know, if you go back to
1917 and the Balfa declaration, which is
only a sort of public letter from from
the foreign secretary of the then
government or whatever he whatever
Belfer's position was in the government
to a banker, a Jewish banker, albeit
Lord Rothschild, saying um we look
favor, her majesty's or his majesty's
government look favorably upon um the
creation of a homeland for the Jewish
people in the but let's not forget Yeah,
the letter the Balfa declaration is only
that long,
>> right?
>> And the second sentence says always
being understood that the civil and
legal and what religious rights of the
indigenous people of Palestine are not
affected detrimentally in any way. Whoa.
We forgot that bit about the Balflow
Declaration, didn't we? So Balfa didn't
say, "Oh, and this government looks
favorably upon you going in and
murdering them all and stealing their
washing machines and TV sets and all
their olive trees and their streams and
their mountains and their access to the
Mediterranean Sea, for instance, and all
the rest of it, and destroying them
down to the L and doing the Amalcch
thing, which Netanyahu is so keen on
bringing up and will kill all their pigs
and goats and sheep and all their swine
and blah and on and on and on. It didn't
say that. I'm not saying that the Balfur
declaration was a good thing. It was a
terrible idea.
>> Terrible.
>> Yeah.
>> And it always will be. any colonial
notion like that of a people going into
a populous a populated seriously
populated country with its own in let's
not forget as well that for hundreds of
years hundred thousands of years the
people in that somewhat desert but also
very fertile in some places had been
living together with their different
Abrahamic religions including Judaism,
Christianity and the Muslim religion for
hundreds of year. Well, at least 2000
since since Christianity was in its
infancy, which was 2000. All been living
cheek by jail.
Yeah. All right. The crusaders went in
there in the 15th century or the 14th or
wherever it was, and did quite a lot of
murder and mayhem cuz they were demented
and they came from England for goodness
sake. And they were in cahoots with a
bunch of bankers and people. It's very
like Balfur and Rothchild in its own
weird way.
>> But
but nevertheless, nobody has ever denied
that it was when when you look back even
early photographs pre- Nakba of what
Palestine was like. Bustling streets,
busy, busy, busy, busy. It was a kind
very important uh gateway between uh
Western Europe and the Orian. There's a
very spe it's it's no surprise that
there's been this much blood shed about
that particular piece of real estate.
But the fact that we're still doing it
now is insane and we all know it. All of
us in the choir and we are going to
stand shouldertosh shoulder. We ordinary
people John as you and me you and I and
Rebecca know we are the ordinary people
standing shoulder from the river to the
sea. We will turn this ship around
because we are right and they are wrong.
And it's not just we might be right at
514. No, we're right 99 to1. It's got
to, you know, they talk about the 1%. It
may be that only 1% are actually
criminally insane like Donald Trump and
Netanyahu and Kama and that the other
99% of us are reasonably sane and good
and you know well
empathetic human beings who care for all
our brothers and sisters irrespective of
their religion or nationality or
ethnicity or anything else cuz we're all
you're human beings and we would never
and we could never ever ever drop a
bomb, a single bomb somewhere where
there was a child that we might damage
even if we only damaged them mentally
cuz it's a loud bang and [gasps] and
they spend the rest of their lives
scared out of their skins because that's
what we've done to them. Why? Because
we're greedy. Donald,
you are a greedy thug. Kama, you are a
greedy thug. Macarron, you're they're
all greedy thugs.
They should all be in looney bins. And
we the people should be using some of
our hard earned money to pay taxes to
have nice nurses and strong men in white
coats to look after them and make sure
they don't do any more damage cuz
they're crazy. And we all know it.
That's the sick thing is it's so obvious
that they are [clears throat] crazy.
Roger, I want to ask you about the
reception that you've received around
the world for your your activism on
human rights and especially on
Palestine. There's a huge swath of the
public here in the United States where
you have saintly status, including in my
house, but you've faced real push back,
especially in Germany. My own humble
opinion, and we we talked about this at
the beginning of the of the
conversation, is that the Germans are
are knee-jerk pro-Israel because they're
ashamed of their Nazi past. Yeah.
>> And they're unable to control themselves
and going too far in the opposite
direction. But
>> they are supporting the Israeli
government in policies that in many ways
mirror the policies of Germany in the
1930s and the 1940s.
>> Yeah.
>> Tell tell us what you face as you travel
and speak out on these issues. What what
are what are people saying to you?
Well, they try and cancel my they try
and they try and cancel the shows and
they use lawfare, warfare, anything they
can. Uh in Germany for instance, no
newspaper will ever speak to me or
nobody will ever interview me or nobody.
I'm ab I am verboten. I um there was one
thing Deutsch Deutsch Sait one newspaper
did it and it was very slanted but at
least he was called Alexander Gorov was
the name of the journalist at least he
spoke to me and they did sort of print
it but you know I write in my in my
memoir I write about being on the top
floor of a hotel in Berlin
I can't remember the name of the hotel
it has a beautiful cathedral next door
to it with a beautiful cop copper domed
roof. But in front of my room looking
down, there's a piece of glass in the
middle of the cobblestones. And it's
actually a memorial to the book burning
that took place in September 1933. I
think it was September, maybe it was
earlier, maybe it was even May 1933
where they and it's on the place where
in that particular cobbled square in
Berlin, they the Nazis burned a huge
pile of books in front of. So, it's
fascinating that the other way that they
try
to deal with me, and this happened more
in South America later on in 2023, they
won't let me stay in a hotel.
>> What?
>> Yeah. No, seriously, you can't stay in a
any hotel in in Buenosares in Argentina.
I I I couldn't I only went I only went
to Argentina on my last tour which was
the Tinad tour and this was have been in
November 2023 so it's after October the
7th I had to fly in borrow an apartment
from some like Michael you told cuz I
couldn't stay in a hotel anywhere and
then leave immediately after the second
gig before the so I stayed one night in
Buenos. This is a town where a few years
before I had done nine consecutive
soldout shows, breaking all records in
the River Plate Stadium, 65,000 people a
night for nine shows, you know, and at
the end of night I went, I'm not doing
anymore. This is crazy. But it was also
very, you know, so I I was the most
popular artist by far and I couldn't get
a room in a hotel because the Israeli
lobby said, "No, we want him dead." No,
he there is no room at the end for this
guy. He doesn't believe in murdering
people and stealing their land. Well, we
do. So,
>> you know, and how ironic is it that
Germany was the home to so many escaped
Nazis after the Second World War?
>> You mean Argentina? H I'm sorry,
Argentina. Thank you.
>> Yeah. Yeah, exactly. That I I believe
that the Israeli hierarchy, and there's
some circumstantial or even physical
evidence to support this, is that
they're looking at at Patagonia now as
to where they may have to go when Israel
finishes. They are all going to have
prices on their heads and they're going
to and they're looking for places to go.
And that South America is one of the
things that they're looking at. I mean,
I can smile. I mean, I the idea that
Smrich and Bengavir and Netanyahu will
end up in, you know, living in Argentina
actually makes me happy so long as
they're not in the Holy Land. I don't
care where they end up frankly
that because they are such disgusting
monsters, you know that that we but
retribution is the is at the bottom of
our list. It's at the bottom of my list.
The top of my list is any single child
getting the help that it is going to
need to transcend
the horror that none of us will ever
ever be able to even begin to understand
of of what's been done to them in
Palestine since 1948. I'm not just
talking about since October the 7th,
2023. I'm talking about 80 years of mon
of a monster, a rampant raging
ethno and religio supremacist monster
tearing the throats out of their young
and throwing the remains to one side and
kill them. Kill them all. We are the
chosen ones. And you might say people
say, "Oh, he's being antiatic. How dare
he talk about this? It's not me. They
are the ones who claim that they're
chosen by Wahi or whatever his name is
and that they have they are so superior
that they have completely different laws
for them. I often say, you know, it's
like when Algra Petro took me all over
the West Bank in 2007. We I we went
everywhere and and she was working for
UNRA at the time. I think Unur Yeah, I
think so. So, we were in UN vehicles and
they were practically spitting on us
just cuz we were in UN vehicles and but
what am I trying to say here? Yeah. Oh,
yeah. I remember her saying to me, I
said, "Well, at least they have nice
roads. This is in the West Bank." And
she said, "Yeah, but these roads are
only to get to the settlements. The
local people aren't allowed to drive on
these." I said, "Don't be stupid." She
said, "No, you can't drive on these
roads. you can because you're a visiting
British pop star, but local people, you
can't use these roads unless you're
Jewish. And I said, well, so it's like,
imagine this. If you're American,
imagine you arrive at the New Jersey
Turnpike and go to get on through the
booth or whatever and and you have to
show your papers and they go, "Oops,
you're not a Christian. You can't go on
this road." What? Don't be [__] dar.
That's absurd. Well, that's the law.
Well, that's the law. You can't go on
this road unless you're Jewish. What?
No. No. I don't believe you. This is
absolute nonsense. This is why we fought
the Second World War against the Nazis,
you morons, is so we wouldn't have to
deal with any of this uber and
unmentioned bollocks ever again cuz it's
nonsense. I mean, if we take it further,
we now know because of work done by
biochemists in the um in the 1990s, we
know all about the human genome. We now
know that we're all African.
>> Dopey.
>> That's right.
>> Just cuz he looks Chinese and you don't
and you're darker skinned than he is,
doesn't mean we're not all homo sapiens.
We are. We share the same DNA. We are
all cousins. We look different cuz we
went and lived in different bits of the
globe and we intermarried
with the ones who were living near us.
And the climate was different. And so we
we we developed in different ways, but
as far as we know and we we're pretty
good at this stuff now. That is why
human beings some human beings look
different than others. And so the it's
all you know the it's all absolute
nonsense. But I and I think for my part
as well I get I come under attack a lot
because I'm an atheist. And so I I
sometimes put down the holy scriptures,
you know, saying you shouldn't take this
[__] too seriously. Nobody knows where
it came from. It was all written or
certainly all the gospel, the Christians
[__] was all written at least 150 years
after any of it took place. So it's all
a bit of hearsay and what happened. And
you know how bad we are. We all know we
know now because we have scientific
proof of this that eyewitness reports of
things are totally unreliable. Even
somebody who was there nearly always
gets it wrong.
And and the human brain will make all
kinds of [__] up just because it's
convenient or because it's funnier or
because it's more, you know, helpful to
them and their side of an argument or
what what happened. Well, I think so.
It's very Montipython in its own weird
way. So, but so we we do we are lucky
enough now to know an awful lot about
uh genetics and DNA. I mean, if you
think the double helix thing that came
out of Cambridge University when I was a
teenager, we didn't know anything about
any of that in the 40s or the 50s,
nothing. And then suddenly Wilson and
whoever the other bloke was,
>> yes,
>> you know, discovered it.
>> They discovered it. They discovered it
and they went, "Here's the model and
this is what it looks like and this is
what it does." And we all went, "Wow,
that's fascinating." And it is and it's
great to know. But human knowledge is
only I often like to think of it, human
knowledge is only like it's like a dock
being pushed out into a limitless ocean
that goes further than we can possibly
imagine. We'll never know everything
about everything. I think knowing what
little we do about the universe and the
limit and the limits or non-limits of
space and blah blah blah blah, we must
at least now know enough to know that we
can't know everything and we never will.
But all this stuff about this god or
that god or the other god is all sort of
guessing. Anthropology
and anthropological
um investigations into tells us a lot
because people who lived in deep valleys
they have a completely different
religion than people who lived in
deserts and could see lots of stars and
all of that. You know, it depends who
you are and where you are, what you
figure out and the stories that you make
up in order to fill in the g that huge
gap.
So, I I know I'm wondering I'm I'm
wandering off case now because that none
of this has Okay, none of this has
anything to do with the fact that it
there's a reason why we get addicted to
Tik Tok of saving animals trapped in
bobbed, which we do. I do. I know that's
why I doom scroll sometimes is because
I'm addicted
>> to seeing love being expressed for
baby animals, plant. It doesn't really
matter what it is because we're capable
of it and because it's kind of
attractive to it. So, um
so we s we sort of know that we can be
good if good means helping each other.
So somebody comes knocking at the door
and you they're hungry, you feed them.
>> If they're cold, you give them shelter.
These are the basic human rights that
you and I believe all our brothers and
sisters. They should have free firstly
they should have freedom to life. Nobody
should ever be allowed to kill even one
of us. Never. Ever. Ever. Rule one.
Funnily enough, it's in the holy scripts
as well. It's called the sixth
commandment in the Abrahamic. Thou shalt
not kill. That's first thing. But then
there's a right to food, shelter, and
possibly
education maybe
>> medical medical care. Let's call those
the five basics. You know, we believe in
that. I believe in it. I I I think
that's absolutely that is the platform
upon which I stand
>> and it's not complicated and it's very
small. It is the universal declaration
of human rights made by the fledgling
United Nations on the 10th of December
in Paris in 1948.
That is my platform and I defy anybody
on the other side of any political
argument to stand up against me in a
debate and say no that that's not
important. You're wrong about that,
Roger. Well, what is more important than
that then? And and there is no answer to
that except this. Well, the answer
actually is that some of the animals is
Orwell got it right in Animal Farm. Some
of the animals are more equal than
others. We
Mr. Netanyahu is way more important
than him over there cuz he's an Arab and
I'm a Jew and God tells me that I'm far
more important. So, you're wrong. There
should absolutely universal human rights
is the worst idea that anyone has ever
had
and that's what they believe.
>> Yeah, unfortunately they do. I have one
one final question for you. It's
something that I struggle with a lot. Um
and this is how
you've had to confront um these specious
accusations of anti-semitism. So many
people all over the world conflate
anti-semitism with anti-ionism. And
indeed, I was talking to an Israeli man,
a young Israeli man this past weekend,
and he told me that in the school system
in Israel, they are actually taught to
accuse anybody who criticizes Israel in
any way uh to accuse them of of
anti-semitism.
How should we confront this? What advice
would you give? Listen to Nurret Ped
Elhanan who's a friend of mine. She
teaches this in university in Jerusalem.
She teaches her main thesis has been how
uh school books in Israel are set up to
create Nazis. That's what they're for.
It's a exact parallel with uh with
Germany in in the 1930s and 1940s.
So, um, yeah, it's actually there's no
conversation to be had really because
we're 100% right and they're 100% wrong.
And if they can't see, you can't you
cannot tell a raging Christian Zionist,
you know, uh, Mike Huckabe is a perfect
example that he's wrong, that his
reading of the Bible is nonsense.
No, Jesus isn't coming back down. And
he's not going to take your hand and
Mike Pence's and flatter off into heaven
with Jesus with Mike Huckabe and Mike
Pence. Can you? Poor Jesus. Oh my god.
Imagine spending all eternity with Mike
Huckabe and Mike Pence. Oh, well,
obviously he's not going to do that. And
and it's nonsense. It's obviously
complete insane nonsense. But when you
live in small communities out in the
Midwest, you sometimes be but start
talking in tongues and believe that
being bitten by snakes is a good thing
and all that crap. It's it's Yeah, it's
complete nonsense. Obviously, it's for
people who can't read, who don't read
books except the Bible. You know it this
is this is the same people who ducked
witches back in Salem in the you know
17th century or the 16th it's not it's
all it's crazy nonsense we all know it
but they still believe it sadly and they
can do an enormous amount of damage.
Now, why they all do it, we would need
to ask Gabbor mate, you know, I I've got
a lot of time for Gabbor because a
because of his his background as a
Holocaust survivor and growing up in
Hungary and so, you know, his um being
exposed to Stalinism and all that bad
stuff as well early early in his life.
But he his all the work that Gabbor has
done uh on childhood trauma I think is
fundamentally important to all of us and
to understanding why Christ imagine what
Netanyahu's young life must have been
like growing up in Brooklyn. We don't
hear much about it but he it he could
not have turned into this monster
without there being defining. I'd love
to hear what Gabos's theor Gabbor Mate's
theory would be about Netanyahu, not to
mention Bengavir and Smootri and the
others and and people like Ron Durma.
You know, I was having a conversation
many many what 30 or 40 30 years ago I
maybe not quite that with another Ron.
What the hell was his name? Ron, he was
very very rich. He's recently lost all
his money. um Pearlman,
his name was Ron Pelman and he owned his
mother I think left him a cosmetics
company. So he owned a huge cosmetics
anyway lived out here for my sins a
number of marriages ago. I went to a
party once at his house or something and
he was you know well I don't want to
speak ill of him because I hardly knew
him except he was very very wealthy and
that doesn't usually do do you anyway
one night the phone rang and it was him
and he said I want you to speak to the
other Ron so I went Rono and before I
could somebody and it was Ron Durma who
is now I don't know what he is in the
current government in Israel but he he
tried to bend my ear to persuade me that
I was making a terrible mistake in
speaking out against Israel at the 20
years ago or whatever.
>> But I thought it was fascinating and
they have tried from time to time.
They've tried to get at me in all kinds
of ways to try and deviate from from my
path
>> and I and and I you know I always go I
go it's my platform's tiny. It's just
the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights. Either you believe in it or you
don't. I do, you don't. That's why you
won't let me stay in the hotel
because you hate the idea that human
rights even exist. You don't want human
right. I do. I do. So that's at least
the line is clear. It's a clear line and
it's drawn in the sand and I know that's
what it is. Donald Trump doesn't believe
in human rights. Joe Biden didn't
believe. Camala Harris, none of the
politicians with the possible exception,
you know, of Rashida Talib and maybe
Elan Omar and maybe one or two white blo
as well believe in human rights, but
very few and they don't and very very
few. So, so it's a huge issue. Should we
take this seriously? Do we what about
international law? Do should we have
international Yes, please. Yes, please.
And they go, not really.
other countries should do as we tell
them, otherwise we'll kill them. That's
a much better system. Uh
anyway,
>> indeed,
>> I'm rambling again.
>> Well, that's okay. Roger, I want to
thank you again for doing this. Such a
treat. Roger Waters is one of the most
successful singer songwriters on the
planet as both a founding member of Pink
Floyd and a solo act. But even more
importantly, he is one of the clearest
voices in the [music] world in defense
of human rights and uh and civil rights
and civil liberties for the Palestinian
People.